Speaker 1: again naturally.
Speaker 2: And later in the episode, we'll have our calm word tour, where we go over some useful words, idioms and phrasal verbs from today's conversation.
Speaker 1: So while we talk about habits that can change your life, you'll also build your English in a natural way.
Speaker 2: And before we begin, we want to ask
Speaker 1: you something. What is one healthy habit you keep promising yourself, but keep breaking up with?
Speaker 2: That is such a dramatic way to say it.
Speaker 1: But it's true.
Speaker 2: Honestly, sleeping on time.
Speaker 1: Strong answer.
Speaker 2: Embarrassingly strong.
Speaker 1: Mine is saying, I'll just check one thing on my phone.
Speaker 2: Ah, yes. Modern history's least honest sentence.
Speaker 1: Truly.
Speaker 2: Alright, let's get into it.
Speaker 1: Okay, can I start with a slightly uncomfortable truth?
Speaker 2: Depends. Is it one of those truths that sounds wise in the morning and annoying at night?
Speaker 1: Yes, exactly that kind.
Speaker 2: Go on then.
Speaker 1: Most people already know what a healthy habit looks like.
Speaker 2: Yes, that's so true.
Speaker 1: People know sleep matters. People know movement matters. People know stress matters. So usually the problem is not information.
Speaker 2: Right. Nobody hears vegetables are good for you and whispers. This changes everything.
Speaker 1: Exactly.
Speaker 2: The hard part is not knowing. The hard part is living.
Speaker 1: Hmm, real life is where everything gets messy.
Speaker 2: Because real life is weird. You're tired. Your phone is glowing. Your mood is unstable. And suddenly the healthy plan you made at 8 a.m. feels like it was written by another person.
Speaker 1: Morning you is very ambitious.
Speaker 2: Morning me has hope.
Speaker 1: Night you has snacks.
Speaker 2: Sadly yes.
Speaker 1: And that's why this first point matters. Healthy habits are not only actions. A lot of the time they're identity choices. Hmm, say more. A habit gets stronger when it stops feeling like a random task and starts feeling like part of who you are.
Speaker 2: Yes, like saying I'm someone who takes care of my body instead of I'm trying to be healthier this week.
Speaker 1: Exactly. The second one feels temporary. The first one feels personal.
Speaker 2: And that's why the word here is intentional.
Speaker 1: Right. If something is intentional you do it on purpose with awareness, not randomly, not just because the day dragged you somewhere.
Speaker 2: And honestly that already feels healthier, even before the habit becomes perfect.
Speaker 1: Because a healthy life is built through small intentional choices that repeat quietly over time.
Speaker 2: So maybe the better question is not what habit should I copy, but what do I want my daily choices to say about me?
Speaker 1: That is such a better place to begin.
Speaker 2: But even when people know who they want to be, there's still another problem.
Speaker 1: Hmm, the environment.
Speaker 2: Yes, your environment is often stronger than your willpower.
Speaker 1: It really is.
Speaker 2: People say why do I keep eating biscuits? While the biscuits are in a clear jar on the counter like confident little villains.
Speaker 1: Or why do I keep checking my phone at night while the phone is literally beside the pillow?
Unknown: A
Speaker 1: toxic bedtime companion. And this matters because people blame themselves too quickly. They say I have no discipline. When sometimes their whole setup is working against them.
Speaker 2: Hmm. Your room matters. Your desk matters. Your kitchen matters. Your notifications matter. What you see first matters.
Speaker 1: It's like trying to walk forward while the floor is quietly moving backward.
Speaker 2: Yes, exactly.
Speaker 1: I had this with sleep. I kept saying I wanted to sleep earlier, very serious, very mature. But every night my laptop was open, my phone was charged, and I had no real bedtime routine.
Speaker 2: So basically your environment said no, we're staying awake.
Speaker 1: Exactly.
Speaker 2: And this is where the word detrimental fits.
Speaker 1: Yes, if something is detrimental, it's harmful. It quietly makes things worse for you.
Speaker 2: And sometimes the most detrimental things are not dramatic. They're just always there.
Speaker 1: Constant noise, constant temptation, constant easy distraction. So
Speaker 2: instead of asking why am I so weak, maybe a better question is, what around me keeps making the unhealthy choice easier?
Speaker 1: That question is kinder and smarter.
Speaker 2: Because sometimes the problem is not your character, sometimes it's your setup.
Speaker 1: And once you see that, another truth becomes clearer too.
Speaker 2: A lot of unhealthy habits are not really about pleasure.
Speaker 1: Hmm, they're about comfort.
Speaker 2: Yes, many unhealthy habits are emotional coping tools.
Speaker 1: That point matters a lot.
Speaker 2: Because sometimes people say I'm lazy, when the real story is I'm overwhelmed.
Speaker 1: Or lonely.
Speaker 2: Or mentally tired. Or trying to feel better quickly.
Speaker 1: Exactly, stress eating, doom scrolling, staying up too late, drinking too much coffee. A lot of these habits are emotional before they are practical. They
Speaker 2: give temporary relief.
Speaker 1: Even when tomorrow has to pay for it. Yes. I had a season like that once. I was overworking, under -sleeping, drinking coffee late, answering messages at silly hours and calling it responsibility. Hmm. But really, I was just pushing myself too hard every day.
Speaker 2: You were burning the candle at both ends.
Speaker 1: Right. If you burn the candle at both ends, it means you're doing too much and using too much energy without enough rest.
Speaker 2: It sounds impressive.
Speaker 1: It does. Very adult. Very productive.
Speaker 2: Meanwhile, your nervous system is writing a complaint.
Speaker 1: Exactly.
Speaker 2: And that's why I think the better question is not only how do I stop this habit, but what is this habit doing for me emotionally? Is
Speaker 1: it giving comfort, escape, numbness, relief?
Unknown: Because
Speaker 2: if you remove the habit without understanding the need underneath it, something else often takes its place.
Speaker 1: That's like taking away the umbrella without stopping the rain.
Speaker 2: See? That's why metaphors help.
Speaker 1: They really do. And then there's another layer to all of this.
Speaker 2: Hmm. Modern life itself. Yes,
Speaker 1: modern life rewards unhealthy patterns all the time.
Speaker 2: It absolutely does. Sit more, scroll more, sleep less, order faster, reply now, keep going. Do not be still for even five minutes.
Speaker 1: That really is the modern lifestyle speech.
Speaker 2: And that's why people sometimes feel like they're failing privately. When actually, they're fighting something much bigger.
Speaker 1: Because a lot of unhealthy choices are designed to be easy. Convenience is not always on your side. Rest
Speaker 2: takes intention, walking takes intention, cooking takes intention. But distraction? Distraction is already open.
Speaker 1: Yes, the unhealthy option is often the default option.
Speaker 2: Your phone never says, are you sure you want to lose 40 minutes to nonsense?
Speaker 1: No, it says, here are three more things that will steal your attention. Exactly. And this is where cut back on fits really well.
Speaker 2: Right. If you cut back on something, you reduce it. Not necessarily to zero, but to a healthier amount.
Speaker 1: And I like that phrase because it feels realistic.
Speaker 2: Yes. Cut back on scrolling. Cut back on constant noise. Cut back on stress snacking. Cut back on always being available.
Speaker 1: It sounds like adjustment, not punishment.
Speaker 2: Which matters because a habit only works if it fits your actual life.
Speaker 1: Yes, not your fantasy life. Your real one.
Speaker 2: Not the version of you who wakes up glowing has two free hours every morning and somehow enjoys decorating yogurt with seeds.
Speaker 1: A mythical woman. Truly.
Speaker 2: I
Speaker 1: tried one of those perfect routines once. Wake up early, stretch, journal, read, meditate, make a beautiful breakfast. It looked amazing on paper. Dangerous sentence. By day three, I was annoyed, behind schedule, and weirdly angry at oats.
Speaker 2: Angry at oats is such a specific adult crisis.
Speaker 1: It really is. And that's when I realized the routine was not sustainable. Yes,
Speaker 2: if something is sustainable, it means you can actually continue it over time. It fits your energy, your schedule, and your real life.
Speaker 1: That word changed a lot for me. I stopped asking what looks impressive and started asking what can I actually keep doing. That's such a healthier question. Because a routine you quit after five days is less useful than a small one you can keep for five months.
Speaker 2: Yes, a ten minute walk you actually do is better than a one hour workout you keep postponing forever.
Speaker 1: And that's where moderation matters too.
Speaker 2: Right, moderation means balance, not too much, not
Speaker 1: too
Speaker 2: little.
Speaker 1: Which sounds simple, but people struggle with it because dramatic plans feel exciting.
Speaker 2: Humans love saying from tomorrow everything changes.
Speaker 1: And then tomorrow arrives like good luck with that. Exactly. But moderation is quieter. It asks, what is enough? What is realistic?