Speaker 1: Women in particular became less happy despite all these objective improvements to their lives So to me the the obvious rejoinder to that is well, maybe those objective improvements namely Feminism that's the thing that happened between 1973 and 2008 Maybe that wasn't an objective good. Maybe that was just illusory Well
Unknown: to
Speaker 1: me the obvious
Speaker 2: rejoinder of that is that women are becoming disillusioned with the life they had prior They're like leaving the cave so to speak allegorically and also I don't think you should use self -reported happiness as a metric of Justice or any like objective good because you can plot self -reported happiness with pretty much any variable like highest reported Crime violent crime in the United States also is directly correlated to self -reported happiness This I mean one causes the other note is I mean we should what do you mean by the highest violent
Speaker 1: crime is crime? I'm just saying in
Speaker 2: the periods of time when we've had the most violent crime in the United States There's also a correlation between highest rates of self -reported happiness.
Speaker 1: Well, not not according to the survey I just cited right if happiness has been declining steadily especially for women since 1973 to 2008 You had a major crime spike in the early 90s, but you didn't have a major spike in happiness So perhaps there's some survey that you're referring to in some cities Well, and just but it wouldn't wouldn't but also even
Speaker 2: women living traditional lifestyles are seeing a downfall in happiness So why is it the women who are still living the type of lifestyle that you would probably prescribe to women are also having a decrease in happiness I'm not convinced of the Institute of Family Studies in
Speaker 3: a big and there's a lot of state out there that actually children make you less happy So there is this problem happening happening where we're like, okay, why are people less happy? But we don't know we don't know what it is sure again And then you would expect then that the like if you looked at the most unhappy as countries You would expect Canada the Nordic country Scandinavian countries because they're very egalitarian and you're not seeing that they they actually have higher happiness levels Well, they have the highest rates
Speaker 1: of alcoholism in the world Do you think of Denmark Norway Iceland in particular? I so I don't know happy there now
Speaker 3: you're changing, but if we're gonna just go by what I don't think alcoholic I don't know if I think there are arguments to be made about like community and those things may make people less happy But this idea that's because women aren't having children when we also have data a lot of data that shows children Especially in the United States has the biggest happiness gap And then we're seeing that other countries that are more feminists are also not having like if you compare like Scandinavian countries to like the East like I'm my parents are immigrants from Iran Iran has really high unhappiness levels a lot of countries. Yeah, exactly So I don't know if you can say that this is causing that right?
Speaker 1: Yeah, Nordic countries also have much more homogeneity which is correlated with I agree, but so they're all of those differences, but I think the The point about children making you unhappy and the point about leaving the cave I think those are both a little bit of a cope because they're Be lied by the fact that If it were just that women were coming into their own now And they were recognizing the oppression of which they were not conscious previously Then why would they keep getting less and less happy? You know at a certain point Aren't you supposed to turn the corner and become more happy in your independence? But that's not what's happened for 35 years. It just gets worse worse and worse including relative to men And then for children you look over the past What 70 plus year is in 74 years since 1950 to present day the marriage rate has dropped by 60 % and the birth rate has dropped by 50 % so Just looking at the whole society we are having many many fewer children than we were before and yet we're much less happy
Speaker 3: Even even like like Pakistan or having less kids sure
Speaker 1: I'm just I'm just pointing at you're saying that having fewer children makes you happier And I'm saying we're having many fewer children and Americans are much less happy and you see this even beyond just
Unknown: But
Speaker 1: that's not you
Speaker 4: can't I
Unknown: kind of
Speaker 4: I kind of want to push back on this idea that we've got in more unhappy as time has progressed Because at least to my understanding what's happened in the last like you know 20 or 30 years is an increased awareness of like mental health and what that means So it's not necessarily that people were really happy before and now suddenly are miserable It's just that now we're actually having data where people can talk openly about their mental health unhappiness and not be as Stigmatized as before if we look at the 1950s and even like housewives around that time We see like there is actually like a huge ray of like narcotic usage and basically like prescriptions to that level So I'm not necessarily if I would go as far as to say um Yeah, we've got an unhappiness this time. We've gone more unhappy as time has gone by I would say more likely oh no We've been able to properly report measure and assess mental health as time has gone by
Speaker 1: I mean what listen I'm very inclined towards your view that social scientific studies are bunk I mean, there's a major replication prices. I think it's all ridiculous I will cite those social science stats when they serve my argument because why not that's what we do these days But I agree I'm skeptical of measuring happiness and all the rest of it But on the mental health point, I think here we do have some pretty firm data and it contradicts the argument you're making which is Right now One in five middle -aged women in the country is hooked on anti -depression drugs on any given day. They're taking them Women are two and a half times as likely as men to take these depression drugs It is ubiquitous at this point and and the rates of taking depression drugs Are going up. It's getting much worse. So if we're not getting less and less happy Why do people keep taking more and more depression drugs? No,
Speaker 2: why were housewives in the 50s downing like a bottle of wine at lunch? I'm just saying I'm
Speaker 1: not so sure.
Unknown: I
Speaker 1: mean these are anecdotes
Unknown: that
Speaker 1: we're supplanting self
Speaker 2: -medication now with actually like medically backed drugs that actually help women with their mental health issues I don't know the
Unknown: thing.
Speaker 3: It's also now
Speaker 2: that when you're
Speaker 3: sad You just go to the doctor and they give you anti -depression drugs I don't know how much more depressed people actually are other than the fact that they're just dishing them out to everybody And they're
Speaker 1: dishing them out more and more and more sure you can blame the pharmaceutical industry the medical industry I'm just pointing out you know one what in order to argue against these social science statistics one has to just Turned toward Unfulsifiable anecdotes and memes,
Unknown: you
Speaker 1: know, though the housewives were all miserable in the 50s They were secretly you know drinking behind their husbands backs But I don't know maybe they were maybe they weren't all I have are the data Well the data is just saying that more
Speaker 3: people are on anti -depressants. It's not telling you why it's not telling you what caused it It's not telling you depression. Well, that's what we're debating here is what could have caused it You're saying oh, it's no, but I'm
Speaker 1: not saying you know, maybe they hate their husband Maybe they hate their kids. Maybe they don't like the you know the weather in their town Like I think any great
Speaker 3: example of this anyone now can just be like oh,
Unknown: I
Speaker 3: have trouble focusing This everyone have ADHD or people just getting these like you know These are questions that we should ask before we jump to a conclusion that I
Speaker 1: agree look I think that they're pathologizing a lot of ordinary aspects of human nature But I think part of the reason that we do that is because we're so radically misinterpreting human nature Which brings us right back to feminism The clearest example of this is the transgender argument Which is all anyone ever talks about these days. I'm frankly sick of it We know that men are women are different, but but that shows you You know a major confusion about human nature If a man can become a woman Then we have been really wrong about anthropology for a long time and most reasonable people know man can't become a woman But but that error in human nature goes back much earlier than transgenderism You know,
Unknown: so
Speaker 1: this is why I have pity for the feminists who are trans exclusionary radical feminists Because they don't realize that it was their own ideology that led to this the premise of transgenderism is that men and women are Basically the same so much so that one can become the other but If that's true You know, then that has to come from somewhere and where it came from was the redefinition of marriage to say that a man and a woman is the same as man And a man is the same as a woman and a woman and that comes from the sexual revolution and that comes from feminism Which says a woman needs a man like a fish needs a bicycle So yeah, I agree these errors in human nature can lead to all sorts of problems
Speaker 3: Did you say with transgenderism is people thinking that there's no differences and why would they need to transition?
Speaker 1: That's a great question I
Speaker 3: don't think that's what transgenderism believes that there's no difference between men and women
Speaker 1: transgenderism believes that men and women are so Similar that one can become the other It's which is different than the feminists to say men and women are so similar that a woman can do anything a man can do But transgenderism takes that principle to the extreme which is men and women are so similar They're they're not complementary sex is not immutable It's not an inseparable accident of being as you know in Aristotelian or St. Thomas Aquinas might say But I know it's actually just kind of a social construct and it's so socially constructed that I can go down to my doctor And have them reconstruct my chest and all of a sudden I've magically become the opposite sex that that error comes from Feminist okay
Speaker 2: before we pivot to transgenderism can we go back to the happiness feminist conversation tied up So I wanted to ask you do you think that should be the ultimate good in the metric for which we base like our justice system and our overall societal progress on is self -reported happiness
Speaker 1: Well, I don't know even what you mean by societal progress. I mean, you know Justice is a habit of virtue that inclines the will to give to what he deserves right? So it's it's about desserts right and so we protect certain rights and we enforce certain laws at least we used to we don't really do that as much in this country anymore um and an aspect of political justice would be human flourishing So when we talk about happiness, I'm all I'm very interested in happiness But I'm interested in happiness in the way that Aristotle's interested in happiness, which is you dimonia Yeah, you know a way to live the best possible life And I think that we can know something about that through our faculties of reason which are objective and If reason weren't objective and at least somewhat reliable we couldn't have self -government now the way that happiness is often used In our modern culture is just Is he well as hedonism like the utilitarians where I just need to getting pleasure in avoiding pain Or is just totally subjective To the point where you say well don't yuck my yum, you know, what's Diggus do you listen and despot on to mess, you know, I maybe I like this and you don't like this Well, sure, I mean restaurants have menus for a reason, but there's there must be some limiting principle here We must know something about what is conducive to human happiness And if we don't then how do we have self -government? So I want
Unknown: to
Speaker 1: go back to the agreement.
Unknown: I
Speaker 2: just don't know if self -reported happiness Is more congruent with the subjective reports of happiness or that you dimonia that you're referring to Sure, it's just the best
Speaker 1: we've got I totally agree Something
Speaker 3: you said in the beginning about individualism like do you prefer socio -centric countries? Do you not love America and
Unknown: the American?
Speaker 3: What do you mean
Speaker 1: socio -centric? Like
Speaker 3: countries where like you're like oh part of the problem with feminism is so focused on the self Well, I think that is one of the cornerstones of like western civilization is instead of being It's a very
Speaker 1: liberal view of western civilization Yeah, which I
Speaker 3: think is one of what makes western civilization so wonderful Like we are one of the only cut we I think we are like the only one founded on individualistic rights Like principles that we don't think
Speaker 1: we really are founded that way I think that's what people say we were founded on now But you know you hear a phrase like liberal democracy That's the popular way to describe our country now That phrase appears basically nowhere in the English language until the 30s Then it jumps a little bit in the 40s It really doesn't take off in English literature until the 80s America the founding fathers didn't think of us as a liberal democracy They were influenced by some enlightenment thinkers John Locke and Montesquieu say But they were also influenced by the classical tradition and the classical tradition is one of the common good Not in the communist sense of that but again I don't I don't They thought
Speaker 3: the common good was best pursued by having individual rights Instead of like that's one of the reasons we founded ourselves on a separation of church and state You have the right
Unknown: we
Speaker 3: were not
Speaker 1: founded on a separation of church and state I
Speaker 3: mean we can get into that I think we know
Speaker 1: It's incidental to this point but it appears in no founding document There's one errant letter from Thomas Jefferson to a friend that mentions the phrase And the treaty of Tripoli makes some little knock on Christianity to appease the Muslim pirates who were capturing our sailors But you know the when the first amendment established No church at the national level the reason for that is not that there was a firm separation of church and state It's because they were already established churches at the state level In many states the persisted for decades after the
Unknown: constitution The only
Speaker 1: reference to
Speaker 3: God and the whole thing is that you can't have a test for For political office. They
Unknown: know
Speaker 3: I'm
Unknown: just
Speaker 3: saying purposefully left it out you're saying that this that they didn't know they didn't really have they
Speaker 1: refer to religion explicitly And they say we won't have a church at the national level Because we have churches established a state
Unknown: What
Speaker 1: it
Speaker 3: says that where does it say then the constitution that we're only doing this because we have churches not
Speaker 1: only doing that But we can see it in history and in the ratification debates That's why in a number of states for decades after the ratification you had established churches And this changes through 19th century jurisprudence Unfortunately, but that's you know that has nothing to do obviously with the founding of the country Furthermore, you know you have in the national anthem which come also comes from the 19th century The notion that this be our motto and God is our trust which is from a forgotten verse of the the Star Spangled Banner you also have it in our money You also have it in the benedictions and the invocations of the continental congress and the constitutional convention So you also have in the speeches of George Washington And so you know John Adams says that the constant that the American government will be based on the Christian morality John Jay first Chief Justice of the United States is The same thing he goes he